You got to stop your testosterone for a
month.
>> Let's talk about the reasons uh that
some men have for stopping TRT. I read
that a lot also in the Facebook group uh
we manage. Um yeah, it didn't work for
me. I just stopped. Uh do you hear that
a lot in your practice?
>> Yeah, I don't have a lot of guys that
stop. I've had a few that just feel like
Yeah, I mean we've tried multiple things
and it just never ticked the boxes they
wanted it to. I will I will say usually
that is all about and I try to do this
at the very beginning. Set expectations.
Expectations in life are everything.
>> Yeah.
>> What is somebody expecting to happen
versus what is appropriate to expect,
you know, and so there's a mismatch
there. A lot of guys think that when
they get on testosterone, it's going to
turn them into Arnold Schwarzenegger or
they're going to be this way in the gym
or they're going to look this way or
they're going to want to have sex with
their wife now every day. And it's like
that's not true. uh even though we set
those expectations up front, some guys
still have it in their head based on
buddies they're talking to or stuff
they're reading online and they get that
in their head and then they're
disappointed when that doesn't happen.
And and I get it. That's that's totally
legit. If that if it's not right for
them, it's not right for them. Um I
think in a lot of group the group we see
guys stop because they were given pretty
crappy protocols to begin with. So
they're being thrown on aromatase
inhibitors, poor injection frequencies,
uh not willing to explore symptom
resolution, frequent phbotoies, all the
things the red flags we talked about
that will drive people away because
they're like, "Yeah, I got on this and I
was promised the world and I actually
got worse." Uh and that's a red flag
when you see guys in general, people
should not get worse if you're if you're
doing TRT the right way in my opinion.
Um, now there can be some transient time
periods where things get worse, like
those first four to six weeks or a
couple months with water return and
weird things happening because your
body's just got to get used to it. That
would be another reason people probably
prematurely stop is they're not willing
to give it enough time. A lot of guys
think that these results are going to
come quicker than they should. Um, and
then they get frustrated. They're like,
"Oh, I've been I mean, I had a guy who
was like on it two weeks. He's like, "I
don't feel any different." I'm like, "I
know. We we talked about this many
times. Like, you're not going to feel
different yet. It's this is a a long
haul thing and you still have to work on
your lifestyle. That's the other thing.
A lot of guys drop out because they're
not willing to address all the things.
Now, some do. Some come and they're
hitting all the boxes already. Those are
the guys that generally get better on
TRT, right? Because they're already
doing all the right stuff, but there's
still that one missing piece. Throw that
in and like, "Yep, that was it. I'm
great. I'm good." But these guys that
like you try to really talk to about all
their multiaceted variables in their
life and they acknowledge it, but then
they get on the testosterone. They just
want it to do all the work and then they
get disappointed when that doesn't
happen. And I'm like, have you changed
your diet? Show me what Oh, well, no,
we're still busy. We're still doing I'm
like, there's no excuses. Those are
excuses, but you can overcome them.
Like, you just have to want it. And
that's I mean, that's like with anything
in life. If you truly want it, you'll
make it happen. You know, in general,
especially when it comes to dietary
choices and food. I mean, anybody can
make enough food on a Sunday and a
Wednesday to last them the whole week. I
mean, you just can. Um, it doesn't have
to be anything fancy. You know, I ate
ground beef and rice for lunch every day
and I got leftover the next day. It's
not hard. Uh, it takes me 10 minutes,
you know, to do that. So, um, I do think
that's a big part of it though is is and
that's not just in the hormone world.
That's in a lot of things in life is
people are expectations are not properly
set and then people get disappointed
when their own expectations aren't met
and they drop out and it's like well you
had the wrong expectations on that.
That's not everybody. There are some
people it just doesn't it just doesn't
work. You know, it doesn't tick the
right boxes for whatever reason. A lot
of guys will drop out for fertility
purposes because they're told they have
to. Not in my clinic. Uh I've had a few
that do it on their own and then come
back and tell me and I'm like, "Why
didn't you reach me?" like like I can
walk you through this, you know, that's
why I'm here. That's part of the model.
Uh I'm available all the time. Um
because I would tell them, "No, we can
do FSH, HCG, all these other things, and
it works almost every time." So, but a
lot of guys are ripped off their
testosterone from their providers to
quote unquote regain their fertility,
and then they feel like crap. Um so,
that would be another dropout, even
though it's not really necessarily a
voluntary one probably on their part,
per se, but um they're they're being fed
something that's not true. And the same
thing with hematocrit stuff like they'll
be told you've got to you know I see
primary care providers all the time
that'll tell people they'll check their
hematocrit and it'll be 54 and they're
like you got to stop your testosterone
for a month. It's like what what is
wrong with you? What are you talking
about? Like 10 years ago 55 was normal
top of normal range like first of all
but they don't even know that. So it is
what it is. But those would probably be
the main reasons for dropout. I would
say poor protocol and wrong
expectations. And could it also be that
um they don't feel optimized yet because
they need some other hormone optimized
like DHEA or pregnnolone?
>> Maybe. I haven't quite seen that yet. As
far as the dropout part, I've had a few
guys where we did add like pregnnolone
and that ticked the one remaining box,
but they were never going to stop their
TRT because of that. Yeah, that was an
an extra thing where you're trying to
tease through and go, well, can we find
something else that might tick that box?
In general, I've only seen that a few
times. I'm I'm not a huge pregnant alone
DHA fan. I think Prague over DHEA. DHEA
is kind of dirty to me uh in general as
far as the effects I've seen in a lot of
guys who try it and myself included. But
everybody's different. I know Dave's a
big fan of it. Uh but I think he he
would agree it depends on the person and
depends on the context. Um but yeah, for
most things they need to dial in their
lifestyles first before they start
searching out other chemicals. That's
the main thing I see. And I see the same
thing with guys on TRT who aren't
getting the gains in the gym that they
think they should be getting. And so
they're like, "Oh, I want to add an I
want to add this." And I'm like, "Send
me your workout routine in your diet
first of all." And they don't they're
not there yet. They're not even close to
being there. And I'm like, "You can't go
start jumping on anabolics when you
don't you're not doing the basics.
Testosterone by itself, even in quote
unquote replacement doses, can do more
than people realize from a muscle
building standpoint. It is very
powerful. I am able to lose fat without
losing muscle in a calorie deficit on
testosterone cream by itself. Nothing
else. Um the myth and fear that I used
to have of of losing muscle, I think
it's because I used to work out the
wrong way when I was dieting and not
have my nutrition dialed in while I was
dieting the right way. Um and now the
testosterone on top, I don't really have
to worry about it. Now, yeah, if I
wanted to get stage lean and still
maintain every ounce of muscle, would I
need to add an anabolic? Maybe. But a
lot of those are cosmetic only. And
that's the other thing people don't
realize about a lot of these things they
want to add. I got guys asking about
adding like anavar to their TRT regimen.
It's like why do you want to add a
methylated steroid? Are you going to
take this long term? Like I wouldn't.
And then in general, those are just
cosmetic effects. Like from a muscle
building standpoint, these are pretty
equal across the board. testosterone,
nandulo anavar, like they as far as
nitrogen retention, all these things,
these markers that they look at, but
it's the other effects people are after
that they want to take. So, a cosmetic
effect from an oral, well, fine. If
you're getting ready for a photo shoot
or a competition, um, but something just
to be on to be on it, like, no, just
work out harder, bump up your
testosterone. If you're g, you know, if
you're going to go the underground
route, try testosterone first. I mean,
really. And if you can't tolerate it,
okay, fine. Try something else. But in
general, people just want to add stuff
to add stuff, I think, because they feel
it's the FOMO, right? It's their fear of
missing out. And they hear all these
people constantly talking. And I used to
have that in the in the performance
world, in steroid world, you always want
to do these exotic cycles, try these
different things. And at the end of the
day, the meat and potatoes basics works.
Low and slow works. You don't need these
gram plus unless you're at that high
level. But if you're just a gym rat
wanting to look better, man, a little
goes a long way. You just need to dial
in your nutrition and your training and
your stress and sleep and the the
hormones are just the icing on the top.